Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
National Park Service, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, College of William and Mary
- Assessment Project Staff Reports/Articles/Papers
  - Jamestown
    - Metz, John. "Exploring the Production and Distribution of Ceramic Roofing Tiles through Acid Extraction." Jamestown Archaeological Assessment Newsletter 2, no. 1 (Summer 1995): 16-20; illus., 1183
      Fragments of ceramic roofing tile from sites in Jamestown and Williamsburg were analyzed to determine links to three seventeenth-century brick and tile kilns, two in Jamestown and one at Bruton Heights in Williamsburg. Roofing tile from Structure 102, one of the Jamestown kilns, and Structure 111, a trash pit, were determined to be related. Likewise, the waster tile recovered from Structure 100 on the Page-Chiles tract was linked to Structure 65, the kiln located nearby. Unexpectedly, Structure 21 was linked to the Bruton Heights kiln. While the results are intriguing, they are only preliminary. The sample size should be increased and more sites included before the results can be considered valid. Includes bibliographical references.
    - Mrozowski, Stephen A. "Contextual Archaeology at Jamestown." Jamestown Archaeological Assessment Newsletter 1, no. 2/3 (Spring/Summer 1994): 1-4; illus., 1184
      Discusses the results of the contextual analysis of Refuse Pit 1, including interpretation of the feature's landscape data and stratigraphic development and evidence of possible plant use in the area. A modified version of a paper presented at the 1994 Middle Atlantic Archaeological Conference meetings in Ocean City, Maryland.
    - Mrozowski, Stephen A., Gerald K. Kelso, and Douglas Currie. "The Use of Contextual Analysis at Jamestown, Virginia." Paper presented at the Annual Conference for Northeast Historical Archaeology, Williamsburg, 1994., 1185
    - Pullins, Steven C. and Dennis B. Blanton. Prehistoric Settlement on Jamestown Island, Archaeological Data Recovery at Site 44JC895 on Black Point, Jamestown Island, James City County, Virginia. Williamsburg: William and Mary Center for Archaeological Research, 2000. 50 pp; illus., charts, maps, photos.
      .... Includes bibliographical references.
    - Riggs, David F. "Jamestown Archeological Assessment." Paper presented at the Northeast National Park Service Curators Conference, New York, June 1995. Summary published in Northeast Museum Services Quarterly 3 (August 1995): 3., 1186
      Provides an overview of the Jamestown project, with emphasis on the role played by the museum collection and archives at Jamestown.
    - ---. "Jamestown Prepares for Quadricentennial in 2007." CRM: Cultural Resource Management 18, no. 10 (1995): 47-48., 1187
      Describes how the Jamestown museum collection and archives at the Colonial National Historical Park are being used in the Jamestown Archaeological Assessment.
    - Stallings, Diane G. "Vibracores, Clovis Points, and Magnetometers: Gaining Insights from an Archaeological Assessment for Interpretive Programs." Paper presented at the annual meeting of the National Association for Interpretation, Billings, Mont., 1996. Published in the 1996 Proceedings of the National Interpreters Workshop., 1220
      Presents insights on how to incorporate information from an archaeological assessment into public interpretive programs.
    - Straube, Beverly A. "The Colonial Potters of Tidewater Virginia." Journal of Early Southern Decorative Arts 21, no. 2 (Winter 1995): 1-40; illus., 1188
      Includes discussion of the potter, or potters, working at Jamestown from ca. 1630-1645, as well as other potters whose products have been found in Jamestown contexts. Artifacts are used to provide evidence of forms and methods. Includes bibliographical references.
    - Training a Lens on Tidewater Country: The Big Picture. Federal Archeology 8, no. 2 (Summer 1995): 22-25., 1189
      A brief description of the Jamestown Archaeological Assessment project. Photographs by Tony Belcastro.
  - Greenspring
    - Brinkley, M. Kent. The Green Spring Plantation Greenhouse/Orangery and the Probable Evolution of the Domestic Area Landscape. Richmond: Uptown Color & Copy Graphics, Inc., 2004. 197 pp; illus., maps, photos.
    - Cultural Resources, Inc. and The James River Institute for Archaeology, Inc. Phase 1 Archaeological Survey of the 196 Acre Green Spring Plantation Site, James City County, Virginia. 1999. 76 pp; illus., maps.
    - Veech, Andrew S. Archeological Investigations - Spring 2001 of the Green Spring "Orangery Wall". Yorktown, National Park Service, 2003. 120 pp; illus, maps, photos.
- Digital Images
  The following URLs are the result of searching "Jamestown" in the VT ImageBase (a digital image database at http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu) on Aug. 7, 2003. In addition to those listed below, 54 digital images are of the 4-H camp in Jamestown at http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/browse.php?folio_ID=/vaes/boxtw/jam
  - Fort at Jamestown, VA [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5708 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5707
  - Jamestown, VA, aerial view [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4841
  - General view of Jamestown with Statues of Captain John Smith, Pocahontas and the ancient church [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4840
  - Ceremony to Commemorate the Establishment of First English Colony [n.d., 1957?] [includes Richard Nixon?]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4858 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4843 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4845 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4852 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4846 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4847 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4844 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4845 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4853 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4842
  - Amphitheater [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4849 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4848
  - Jacqueline Amber House at Jamestown, Virginia site of first Governor's Mansion [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4839
  - Virginia in 1607 - The explorers on board the Susan Constant, looking toward Jamestown Island, just before landing. A group by Robert N.S. Whitelow in the Valentine Museum, Richmond,Virginia, [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5205
  - Jamestown Ter-Centennial Exposition, 1907. [poster?]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4486
  - Jamestown Church, Williamsburg. [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5567
  - Jamestown [ship, n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5712
  - Ships at Jamestown [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5713
  - Jamestown. [oceanside, n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4856 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5710
  - [Jamestown reenactors, n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5709 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4850
  - John Rolfe Home in Jamestown, 1956.
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4837
  - Memorial Gates and Gate House at Jamestown, [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4838 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5711
  - Monument Commemorating the Founding of the First Permanent English Settlement in America at Jamestown, 1931
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5812
  - Old Church at Jamestown - St. Paul's Episcopal Church built in 1739 [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4831
  - Old Church at Jamestown, May 1931
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4832 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4857
  - Play at Jamestown, "The Founders" [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5814 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5815 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5816
  - Re-enactment of the First Settlers in Virginia [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4860 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4861 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4859
  - [audience, ocean view]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4749
  - Robert Hunt Shrine at Jamestown, [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5813
  - Statue of Captain John Smith at Jamestown, [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5810
  - Statue of Pocahontas at Jamestown, [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5811
  - Well at Jamestown "The well at Jamestown where the early colonists drew their drinking water. Many a scrap took place over the possession of this well." [n.d.]
    http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns4836 http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/view_record.php?URN=ns5714